Hello again. You
just learned a lot
about presentation best
practices from my colleague.
Just like you need
to be strategic,
prepared, and clear about
which data you want to share,
you also need to be intentional
about ensuring your
presentations are
accessible and can be
consumed and understood
by everyone.
Let's dive into some
accessibility tips
to set you up for success,
starting with the design
of your presentation.
First, create clear,
simple slides.
Avoid using too many graphics,
too much text, or
too much animation.
Visual complexity makes
it harder for people
to absorb information
during your presentation,
especially for those with
a visual or cognitive impairment.
If your slide uses animation,
make sure that you don't
leave people behind
by making important
content disappear.
If people read more slowly
or rely on an interpreter,
they might need a bit more
time to absorb the content.
Avoid using repetitive animation,
like flashing or flickering,
since it can be distracting
and can trigger seizures.
Simple doesn't have to
mean boring, though.
A simple slide can still be
beautiful and informative.
Just don't try to crowd
too much information or
activity into a single slide.
If you generally don't use
slides when giving a talk,
consider giving it a try—even
if you create just one
slide with your main points.
If you rely only on your voice,
that is, you don't provide
any visual accompaniment,
some people might have
difficulty understanding, whether
because of a language barrier
or hearing or
cognitive impairment.
Another tip is to include
alternative text,
also called "alt text," for
any images, drawings,
or diagrams.
Doing so describes the
information relayed in a graphic
to make it accessible to people
who rely on screen readers.
To add alt text in Google
Slides or PowerPoint,
simply select the object,
right-click, and then
select "alt text."
The same consideration
applies to charts.
Charts can be
difficult to decipher,
especially if they use
a small font in order
to fit more data.
If your slide includes
data-heavy charts or graphs,
be sure to specify the
takeaway either on
the slide itself or
in the speaker notes.
Next, always use text for
critical information.
Never rely only on color or
other visual formatting to convey
critical information
on a chart or slide.
Relying too heavily
on visual formatting
excludes anyone who is
color-blind or unable
to see the screen.
For example, to highlight a
new section of a flowchart,
don't simply use a
different color.
Along with the color change,
add a textual cue,
such as the word "new."
If your presentation
relies heavily on images,
consider including a written
summary at the end of
the presentation
so that people can
read your main points
easily in one place.
Another tip is to
include captions for
video content and in real-time.
Provide captions for all
audio or video recordings
shared in your presentation.
If you're using a YouTube video,
check that the YouTube automatic
captioning is accurate.
If it's not, request
closed captioning through
a captioning service.
Use real-time captioning for
your presentation, if available.
Along with helping deaf or
hard-of-hearing audience members,
real-time captioning
is useful if there
are diverse accents and
languages in the room,
if the presenter
speaks too quickly,
if there are microphone
issues, or if you
have chatty audience members
who are distracting
their neighbors.
Another thing to remember is for
contrast and text
size, more is better.
The difference between text and
its background color is
called contrast ratio.
A high-contrast ratio
makes it easier for
people to read text
or decipher images,
especially if they're
sitting far away
or have low vision
or color blindness.
An ideal contrast ratio is 7:1.
There are contrast checker
tools available online,
so be sure to check those out.
Recommendations for text size
vary, but bigger is
usually better.
Before your presentation begins,
go to the back of
the room and make
sure you can read your slides.
Also, the use of
all capital letters
makes reading texts more
difficult for some people,
such as people with dyslexia.
When possible, avoid
using all caps.
This is a simple change
that can go a long way.
My final tip is to share
your content in advance.
If possible, send slides to
your audience a few days
before your presentation.
This gives the
audience a chance to
review the content, and if needed,
make arrangements to accommodate
their own needs and preferences.
For example, visually-impaired
audience members
might want to follow
along with your slides on
their own device with
screen-reading software.
If you aren't able to share
your slides in advance,
consider sending a document with
a bulleted outline of
your presentation.
If you're using acronyms or
technical or obscure terminology,
include a glossary
with definitions.
This information is
especially helpful
for sign language
interpreters and captioners.
All of these best practices
you just learned will help
make your presentations
accessible
to all of your audience members.
Remember, you can't
communicate information
effectively if your audience
can't easily access it.
For these and other best
practices on how to make
your documents and
presentations more accessible,
check out the resources tab.
Coming up, you will learn about
team communication
and best practices.
Good work so far! You're making
real progress, and I'm
excited to be a part
of your journey.